Guide to the Duke University Progress Pictures Collection, 1925-1932 UA.01.15.0012
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University Progress Pictures collection
1925-1932
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke Construction Company
UA.01.15.0012
3.5 Linear Feet
These photographs were taken during the initial construction of Duke University, 1925-1932. There is one set of pictures for East Campus and two sets for West, and modern copy prints and copy negatives of some images. The collection includes approximately 1000 mounted images in two bound sets (copy 1 and copy 2), along several file folders of mounted and unmounted prints.
approximately 1000 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Duke University Progress Pictures Collection were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1975 and a gift in 1993.
Biographical/Historical note
These photographs were taken during the initial construction of Duke University, 1925-1932. According to the specification books for individual buildings, the contractor was to "furnish to the Architect each month during the construction of the structure, three photographs in duplicate, showing the progress of the work during the preceding month, taken from three different points to be agreed upon and always from the same points. These photographs shall be 8 x 10 inch, mounted on linen, with a hinge on the left hand margin of the photograph."
The Duke Construction Company was formed in 1927 on the advisement of the Building Committee of the Duke Endowment. In a letter to Duke president R.L. Flowers, N.A. Cocke, Assistant Secretary of the Duke Endowment, wrote:
"It is hardly practicable to conduct the operations in the name of the trustees of The Duke Endowment for the reason that The Duke Endowment has no separate entity apart from the trustees, it not being a corporation. On the other hand while the title to the property is in Duke University the Will and Trust Indenture contemplate that the trustees shall erect the buildings for Duke University and turn same over when completed. With the idea, therefore, of establishing some medium for the purpose of carrying on this construction, it has occured to us that it would be wise to form a corporation, known as the "Duke Construction Company" for the sole purpose of constructing these buildings, with a nominal capital stock so that it will clearly appear that this corporation is merely an agency for carrying out this work."
The Duke Construction Company was active in the 1930s and into the 1940s, but it then became dormant and was officially dissolved in 1957.
Scope and Contents note
There is one set of pictures for East Campus and two sets for West, and modern copy prints and copy negatives of some images. One set of the West Campus images (#2) is not accessioned. The other (#1) was received from the estate of W.F. Lee, likely a son of Arthur C. Lee who was the chief engineer for the construction. It is the more complete set (A93-73: five volumes + 25 unbound prints).
Most of the prints are numbered and dated on the front in white ink, and many for West Campus have a number, date, and description of the verso. Some of the prints were made into glass slides; these slides are in the Frank Clyde Brown Papers.
The collection includes approximately 1000 mounted images in two bound sets (copy 1 and copy 2), along several file folders of mounted and unmounted prints. The images range in date from 1925-1932.
The work of at least three photographers is represented in the Progress Pictures. For the East Campus photos, there are prints having the same base number with an A or B suffix, but which were taken on different dates. Some are marked on the verso "from Ramsey Studio, Durham, N.C." and others "Whitney's Camera Craft Shop, 106 1/2 E. Main St., Durham". The "A" and "B" designations are not consistent, and we cannot say that Ramsey was photographer "A and Whitney "B". Ramsey's work predominates in the early photographs and Whitney's in the later. Whitney's work is also represented in the West Campus pictures.
Also in the West Campus mounted prints are pictures marked "C.W. Richardson, Photographer, Duke University" or "Richardson's Photo Service…" According to the Bulletin of Duke University, volume 24, no.7a "The first twenty years" a C.W. Richardson was a member of the staff of the medical art and illustration division, which was started in 1933 (p. 44) and which included photographers. There are also unmounted numbered and unnumbered prints taken by Richardson. Some of these prints are marked News Service or Alumni Affairs. Some mounted West Campus prints are not credited, or if they were stamped by the photographer, the stamp has been covered by the mounting linen. Among the unmounted numbered and unnumbered prints, some are stamped News Service or Alumni Affairs.
The Progress Pictures are offered in jpeg format but are also available as high resolution .tif files.
Related Material
Operations and Maintenance Dept. records, 1919-1957
Duke University Archives
Frank C. Brown papers, 1899-1943
Duke University Archives/Rare Book Manuscript, Special Collections Library
University Archives Photograph collection, 1861-2006
Duke University Archives
University Archives Photographic Negative Collection, 1855-1995
Duke University Archives
College campuses -- Design and construction; College campuses -- Photographs; Construction; Construction projects -- North Carolina -- 1920-1930 -- Photographs; Black-and-white photographs; Photograph albums; Duke Construction Company; Duke University -- Buildings; Duke University -- East Campus; Duke University -- History -- 20th century; Duke University -- West Campus
- East Campus, 1925-1926
  - East Campus Progress Picture #3, 1925 August 15 (Box 1, Print EC3)
    Scope and Contents
    West side of site looking north, with construction equipment.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #4, 1925 August 15 (Box 1, Print EC4)
    East side of site looking north, test walls in the distance.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #5, 1925 September 1 (Box 1, Print EC5)
    West side of site looking north showing excavation for [Lilly] Library.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #6, 1925 September 1 (Box 1, Print EC6)
    East side of site looking north showing excavations and test walls in the distance.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #7, 1925 September 1 (Box 1, Print EC7)
  - East Campus Progress Picture #8, 1925 September 1 (Box 1, Print EC8)
  - East Campus Progress Picture #9, 1925 October 1 (Box 1, Print EC9)
    East side of site looking north showing Alspaugh Dormitory (1902-1926); Library (1902-1927); and Craven Memorial Hall (1898-1927). Excavations and test walls are visible in the distance.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #11, 1925 October 1 (Box 1, Print EC11)
  - East Campus Progress Picture #12, 1925 October 1 (Box 1, Print EC12)
    West side of site looking north showing excavations.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #13, 1925 October 15 (Box 1, Print EC13)
  - East Campus Progress Picture #14, 1925 October 15 (Box 1, Print EC14)
  - East Campus Progress Picture #15, 1925 October 15 (Box 1, Print EC15)
  - East Campus Progress Picture #16, 1925 October 15 (Box 1, Print EC16)
    West side of site looking north showing Alspaugh Dormitory (1902-1926); Library (1902-1927); and Craven Memorial Hall (1898-1927). Railroad tracks are visible behind Craven Memorial Hall.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #17, 1925 November 3 (Box 1, Print EC17)
    East side of site looking north showing excavation for East Campus Union with test walls in the the distance.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #18, 1925 November 3 (Box 1, Print EC18)
  - East Campus Progress Picture #19, 1925 November 3 (Box 1, Print EC19)
  - East Campus Progress Picture #20, 1925 November 3 (Box 1, Print EC20)
    West side of site looking north showing foundations for [Lilly] Library.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #21, 1925 November 3 (Box 1, Print EC21)
    West side of site looking north showing Alspaugh Dormitory (1902-1926); Library (1902-1927); Craven Memorial Hall (1898-1927); and footings for Carr Building. Railroad tracks are visible behind Craven Memorial Hall.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #22, 1925 November 14 (Box 1, Print EC22)
    East side of site looking north showing excavation for East Campus Union. Test walls are visible in the distance.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #23, 1925 November 14 (Box 1, Print EC23)
    West side of site looking north showing foundations for [Lilly] Library and dormitories.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #24, 1925 November 14 (Box 1, Print EC24)
    East side of site looking north showing Alspaugh Dormitory (1902-1926); Library (1902-1927); and Craven Memorial Hall (1898-1927), as well as foundations for Science Building [now Friedl Building].
  - East Campus Progress Picture #25, 1925 December 3 (Box 1, Print EC25)
    West side of site looking north showing foundation for [Lilly] Library. Tennis courts and Trinity Park School Buildings in the distance. Sign warns students to stay out of sites.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #26, 1925 December 3 (Box 1, Print EC26)
    East side of site looking north showing Alspaugh Dormitory (1902-1926); Library (1902-1927); Craven Memorial Hall (1898-1927); Angier B. Duke Gymnasium (the Ark); and Crowell Building, as well as the foundations for Science Building [now Friedl Building].
  - East Campus Progress Picture #27, 1925 December 3 (Box 1, Print EC27)
    East side of site looking north showing work on foundation for East Campus Union. Test walls, Bishop's House, and another residence visible in background.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #28, 1925 December 3 (Box 1, Print EC28)
    West side of site looking north showing foundation for Carr Building.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #29, 1925 December 15 (Box 1, Print EC29)
    East side of site looking north showing Alspaugh Dormitory (1902-1926); Library (1902-1927); Craven Memorial Hall (1898-1927); Crowell Building; Angier B. Duke Gymnasium (the Ark); and the foundation for Science Building [now Friedl Building].
  - East Campus Progress Picture #30, 1925 December 15 (Box 1, Print EC30)
    West side of site looking north showing foundation for [Lilly] Library. Tennis courts and Trinity Park School buildings in distance. Sign warns students to stay out of sites.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #31, 1925 December 15 (Box 1, Print EC31)
    East side of site looking north showing work on foundation for East Campus Union. Test walls, Bishop's House, and another residence are visible in background.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #32, 1925 December 15 (Box 1, Print EC32)
  - East Campus Progress Picture #33, 1925 December 17 (Box 1, Print EC33)
    Foundations for [Lilly] Library and Alspaugh Residence Hall. Flowers House, Dean's residence, Alumni Memorial Gymnasium and Erwin Mills visible in background.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #34, 1925 December 17 (Box 1, Print EC34)
    Foundation for Bassett Residence Hall.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #35, 1925 December 17 (Box 1, Print EC35)
    Foundations for Alspaugh and Pegram Residence Hall.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #36, 1925 December 17 (Box 1, Print EC36)
    Foundations for East Campus Union and Brown Residence Hall. The Angier B. Duke Gymnasium (the Ark) and Crowell Building are visible in background.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #37, 1926 January 2 (Box 1, Print EC37)
    Foundation of Carr Building.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #38, 1926 January 2 (Box 1, Print EC38)
    Foundation for [Lilly] Library.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #39, 1926 January 2 (Box 1, Print EC39)
    Foundation for East Campus Union.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #40, 1926 January 2 (Box 1, Print EC40)
    West side of site looking northwest showing foundations for dormitories.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #41, 1926 January 2 (Box 1, Print EC41)
    East side of site looking southeast showing work on foundations for East Campus Union and dormitories.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #42, 1926 January 2 (Box 1, Print EC42)
    West side of site looking southwest showing foundations for dormitory and East Campus Union. Angier B. Duke Gymnasium (The Ark) is visible in background.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #43, 1926 January 2 (Box 1, Print EC43)
    West side of site showing work on foundations for dormitories. Alumni Memorial Gymnasium is visible in the background.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #44, 1926 January 2 (Box 1, Print EC44)
    East side of site looking northeast showing work on foundation for East Campus Union. Test walls and Bishop's House visible in background.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #45A, 1926 January 2 (Box 1, Print EC45A)
    East side of site looking northeast showing work on foundation for dormitories.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #46A, 1926 January 15 (Box 1, Print EC46A)
    West side of site looking northwest showing foundations for [Lilly] Library and dormitories.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #47B, 1926 January 15 (Box 1, Print EC47B)
    Foundation of East Campus Union.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #48A, 1926 January 15 (Box 1, Print EC48A)
    West side of site looking southwest showing foundations for dormitories. Alumni Memorial Gym is visible in background.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #49A, 1926 January 15 (Box 1, Print EC49A)
  - East Campus Progress Picture #50A, 1926 January 15 (Box 1, Print EC50A)
    East side of site looking east showing foundation for East Campus Union. The Angier B. Duke Gymnasium (The Ark) and Crowell Building are visible at the far right.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #51A, 1926 January 15 (Box 1, Print EC51A)
    West side of site looking north showing foundation for Carr Building. Library (1902-1927) in background.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #52A, 1926 January 15 (Box 1, Print EC52A)
    East side of site looking north showing foundation for Science Building [now Friedl Building].
  - East Campus Progress Picture #45B, 1926 February 1 (Box 1, Print EC45B)
    East side of site looking south showing foundation for Carr Building. Jarvis Residence Hall and West Duke Building in background.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #46B, 1926 February 1 (Box 1, Print EC46B)
    West side of site looking northwest showing foundation for [Lilly] Library.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #47A, 1926 February 1 (Box 1, Print EC47A)
    East side of site looking south showing foundation for Science Building [now Friedl Building]. East Residence Hall and East Duke Building in background.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #48B, 1926 February 1 (Box 1, Print EC48B)
    East side of site looking southeast showing steelwork for dormitory. Angier B. Duke Gymnasium (The Ark) and Crowell Building are visible in the background.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #49B, 1926 February 1 (Box 1, Print EC49B)
    East side of site looking southwest showing steelwork for dormitories. Test walls visible to the right.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #50B, 1926 February 1 (Box 1, Print EC50B)
    North end of site looking south showing foundation for [Baldwin] Auditorium.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #51B, 1926 February 1 (Box 1, Print EC51B)
    Center of site looking north showing foundation of [Lilly] Library and framing for Alspaugh Residence Hall.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #52, 1926 February 1 (Box 1, Print EC52)
    East side of site looking north showing foundations for dormitories. Bishop's House is visible to the right.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #52B, 1926 February 1 (Box 1, Print EC52B)
    East side of site looking north showing foundations for dormitories. Bishop's House is visible in background.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #53, 1926 February 15 (Box 1, Print EC53)
    Center of site looking northeast showing framing of Bassett Residence Hall.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #54, 1926 February 15 (Box 1, Print EC54)
    Center of site looking northwest showing framing of Alspaugh and Pegram Residence Halls.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #55, 1926 February 15 (Box 1, Print EC55)
    East side of site looking south, showing foundation for Carr Building. Jarvis Residence Hall and West Duke Building in background.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #56, 1926 February 15 (Box 1, Print EC56)
    West side of site looking northwest.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #57, 1926 February 15 (Box 1, Print EC57)
    East side of site looking northeast showing foundations and framing for dormitories.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #58, 1926 February 15 (Box 1, Print EC58)
    West side of site looking southwest with view of foundation for [Lilly] Library. Alumni Memorial Gymnasium and houses in background.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #59, 1926 February 15 (Box 1, Print EC59)
    East side of site looking southeast showing foundation for Science Building [now Friedl Building]. Epworth and East Residence Halls and East Duke Building are visible in background.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #60, 1926 February 15 (Box 1, Print EC60)
    North end of site looking northeast showing foundation for [Baldwin] Auditorium.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #61, 1926 March 1 (Box 1, Print EC61)
  - East Campus Progress Picture #62, 1926 March 1 (Box 1, Print EC62)
    East side of site looking northeast showing framing for dormitories.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #63, 1926 March 1 (Box 1, Print EC63)
    East side of site looking south, foundation for Carr Building. Jarvis Residence Hall and West Duke Building in background.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #64, 1926 March 1 (Box 1, Print EC64)
    West side of site looking southeast showing brickwork of [Lilly] Library. Alumni Memorial Gymnasium and houses in the background.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #65, 1926 March 1 (Box 1, Print EC65)
    West side of site looking northwest showing brickwork of [Lilly] Library and Alspaugh Residence Hall.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #66, 1926 March 1 (Box 1, Print EC66)
    West side of site looking northwest showing boxcar and track-mounted crane. [Lilly] Library and Alspaugh Residence Hall in rear.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #67, 1926 March 1 (Box 1, Print EC67)
    East side of site looking north showing foundation of East Campus Union and steel framing for dormitory.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #68, 1926 March 1 (Box 1, Print EC68)
  - East Campus Progress Picture #69, 1926 March 16 (Box 1, Print EC69)
    Center of site looking northwest showing masonry work on [Lilly] Library and dormitory.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #70, 1926 March 16 (Box 1, Print EC70)
    East side of site looking south, foundation for Carr Building. Jarvis and West Duke Buildings in background.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #71, 1926 March 16 (Box 1, Print EC71)
    Middle of site looking southwest showing crane, supplies, and brickwork on [Lilly] Library. Alumni Memorial Gymnasium is visible in background.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #72, 1926 March 16 (Box 1, Print EC72)
    East side of site looking northeast showing railroad cars and framing of dormitory.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #73, 1926 March 16 (Box 1, Print EC73)
    East side of site looking northeast showing foundation of East Campus Union and framing for Brown Residence Hall.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #74, 1926 March 16 (Box 1, Print EC74)
    East side of site looking southeast showing foundation of Science Building [now Friedl Building]. East and Epworth Residence Halls visible in background.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #75, 1926 March 16 (Box 1, Print EC75)
    West side of site looking northwest showing brickwork of Alspaugh and Pegram Residence Halls. [Lilly] Library at far left.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #76, 1926 March 16 (Box 1, Print EC76)
    Middle of site looking northeast showing foundation of [Baldwin] Auditorium.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #77, 1926 April 1 (Box 1, Print EC77)
  - East Campus Progress Picture #78, 1926 April 1 (Box 1, Print EC78)
    West side of site looking west showing brickwork of [Lilly] Library.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #79, 1926 April 1 (Box 1, Print EC79)
    West side of site looking north showing [Lilly] Library and Alspaugh and Pegram Residence Halls.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #80, 1926 April 1 (Box 1, Print EC80)
    East side of site looking southeast showing foundation of Science Building [now Friedl Building]. East and Epworth Residence Halls are visible in background.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #81, 1926 April 1 (Box 1, Print EC81)
    East side of site looking northeast showing foundation of East Campus Union and brickwork and framing of Brown House dormitory.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #82, 1926 April 1 (Box 1, Print EC82)
    Center of site looking northeast showing framing and masonry of dormitories and foundation of East Campus Union at right.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #83, 1926 April 1 (Box 1, Print EC83)
    Center of site looking northwest showing work on [Lilly] Library and dormitories.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #84, 1926 April 1 (Box 1, Print EC84)
    East side of site looking south, showing foundation for Carr Building. Jarvis and West Duke Buildings visible in background.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #85, 1926 April 15 (Box 1, Print EC85)
  - East Campus Progress Picture #86, 1926 April 15 (Box 1, Print EC86)
    East side of site looking north showing foundation and framing of Union Building and dormitories.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #87, 1926 April 15 (Box 1, Print EC87)
    Center of site looking southwest showing scaffolding and masonry work on [Lilly] Library.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #88, 1926 April 15 (Box 1, Print EC88)
    Foundations of [Baldwin] Auditorium, looking northeast.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #89, 1926 April 15 (Box 1, Print EC89)
    East side of site looking southeast showing foundation for Science Building [now Friedl Building]. Epworth Residence Hall, East Residence Hall, and East Duke Building are visible in the background.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #90, 1926 April 15 (Box 1, Print EC90)
  - East Campus Progress Picture #91, 1926 April 15 (Box 1, Print EC91)
    Center of site looking northwest showing scaffolding and masonry work on [Lilly] Library.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #92, 1926 April 15 (Box 1, Print EC92)
    Center of site looking northeast showing railcars and masonry work on Bassett and Brown Residence Halls.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #115, 1926 June 1 (Box 1, Print EC115)
    East side of site looking southeast showing foundation for Science Building [now Friedl Building]. East Residence Hall and East Duke Building in background.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #116, 1926 June 1 (Box 1, Print EC116)
  - East Campus Progress Picture #117, 1926 June 1 (Box 1, Print EC117)
    Scaffolding and masonry on Carr Building.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #118, 1926 June 1 (Box 1, Print EC118)
    Center of site looking northeast showing masonry and framing of Bassett and Brown Residence Halls.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #119, 1926 June 1 (Box 1, Print EC119)
    Center of site looking southwest showing crane, scaffolding, and masonry work on [Lilly] Library.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #120, 1926 June 1 (Box 1, Print EC120)
    North end of site looking east showing Bassett Residence Hall, foundation of [Baldwin] Auditorium, and railcar.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #121, 1926 June 1 (Box 1, Print EC121)
    Center of site looking northwest showing work on [Lilly] Library and Alspaugh Residence Hall.
  - East Campus Progress Picture #122, 1926 June 1 (Box 1, Print EC122)
  - East Campus Progress Picture #113, 1926 June 1 (Box 1, Print EC113)
    East Campus Union with Brown Residence Hall in background.